Who's there?
誰？
I am not human.
我…不是人類
He told me that he has been here for 120 years.
他本人說自己是從120年前來的
Can I change myself?
我有辦法改變自己嗎？
Let's change you!
讓我們一起改變吧
Haruka?
姊姊？
Haruka…!
姊姊…
Haruka, hang in there! Haruka…!
姊姊，你振作一點啊
-Let's take her to hospital. -Yes, please!
-把她送到醫院去吧 -拜託了
It'd be better to drive her there by car. I'll get my keys.
直接開車比叫救護車快，我去拿鑰匙
Haruka…
姊姊…
You were there the whole time?
你剛才在那裡嗎？
Did you see it? What's wrong with my sister? What happened?
你都有看到嗎？ 我姊怎麼了？發生什麼事了？
Is she dead?
她死了嗎？
Of course not.
怎麼可能…
But she will die.
但還是會死
Humans die.
人類是會死的
Why do you say that?
為何要說這種話？
I am sorry.
對不起…
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
-Mr. Fukashi! -Please, hurry!
-深志先生 -拜託了，快點
-It's okay. I'll pick her up. -Thank you.
-我來扛，沒問題的 -不好意思
Did you do something to my sister?
你對我姊姊做了什麼嗎？
What on earth are you?
你到底是什麼？
I…
我…
I cannot live in the human world.
不能在人類的世界活…
Forget it.
已經夠了
-No muscle stiffness. -No, there isn't.
-沒有肌肉僵直的現象啊 -是啊
Check her pupils.
確認瞳孔
Does your sister have any allergies?
你姊姊有對什麼過敏嗎？
I think it's anaphylaxis.
我想應該是過敏反應
Do you have any idea what she touched or breathed in?
你知道她有碰到什麼 或摸到什麼嗎？
Mr. Inaniwa, please do me a favor.
學長，我有事拜託你
Yes?
什麼事？
I would like to stay with my sister.
我要陪在姊姊身邊
Would you…
那個人…
go and talk to Mr. Ken Fukashi?
能請你去問問深志研 發生了什麼事嗎？
You mean he knows why this happened to your sister?
你的意思是說 他可能知道你姊怎麼了？
I don't know, but…
我也不知道
Please.
但拜託你了
Hey, where is Mr. Ken Fukashi?
喂，深志研先生在哪？
Not in his room? Maybe he is taking a bath then.
沒在房間裡嗎？還是說在洗澡？
Taking a bath earlier than me? Not in a million years!
要搶在我前面洗澡，還早一百年呢
If I find some pubic hair, I'll kill him.
要是掉了陰毛，我絕對要把他殺掉
I passed by him on my way home from shopping.
我剛才買東西回來路上 有跟他擦身而過
I blew him a kiss, but he walked past without noticing me.
我對他拋了個飛吻 但他沒注意到就走掉了
-No, he just ignored you. -No way!
-那不是沒注意，是無視 -不會吧？
He had been brooding over something.
看起來心事重重啊
Could he have recalled something from his past?
該不會是想起以前的記憶了吧？
Then he went to have a drink alone.
所以一個人跑去喝酒了
Why did he go to have a drink?
他怎麼可能去喝酒啊？
A man goes to have a drink to take a good look at his life.
男人想重新審視自己的人生時 肯定都會去喝酒的啊
Well, just wait. He'll be back soon.
等等吧，馬上就會回來了
Young people nowadays aren't even as responsible as rookies.
身為菜鳥，未免太沒自覺了 現在的年輕人啊
Look who's talking. Child of the pressure-free education generation.
輪不到你說吧 你這個寬鬆世代的小孩
I'm not! And to begin with, I didn't go to school.
我才不是寬鬆世代的呢 我根本沒去上學
I'd nothing to do with it from birth.
一出生就沒什麼餘裕
-You're really cool, Mikoto. -Call me Murozono!
-帥喔，美琴 -叫我室園
I grew up in a poor family like you, Murozono.
我也跟室園小姐一樣 都出生在不幸的家庭
Call me Mikoto.
叫我美琴
Mr. Inaniwa, please try it to see whether it tastes good or not.
社長，吃吃看這個適不適合當下酒菜
What is it? Shimeji mushrooms? You bought a lot.
這是什麼？鴻喜菇啊？ 最近還真買了真多菜啊
Don't just give the workers cheap food! Put some bacon in it!
員工餐可別買些便宜的食材啊 至少放點培根吧
-It's a bit of a waste. -What?
-我想放培根有點太奢侈了 -什麼？
-It's delicious! -Really?
-這很好吃啊 -真的嗎？
It's crunchy and moist!
彈彈脆脆的
It'd be even better if you put bacon in it.
這加培根進去會更棒
-Supermarket Marukame? -No.
-是在丸龜超市買的嗎？ -不
It was growing in the bedding.
放在棉被裡
I saw them growing close together this morning
昨天借給研先生的棉被，今早我一看
when I checked the bedding we lent Ken.
生了滿滿的菇
It's so funny!
真爆笑
Really?
真的嗎？
I see. It's Men's Shimeji, huh?
原來如此，男人的鴻喜菇啊
Damn you! How dare you make me eat that?!
你這傢伙 都給我吃了什麼鬼東西啊？
Tamara, is there any shimeji left there?
玉名小姐，菇還有剩嗎？
Yes, a lot.
還有很多呢
-Tsugumi. -Grandma.
-繼實 -阿姨
How is Haruka?
晴果怎麼樣了？
We have no idea why this happened to her.
我不知道事情為何會變成這樣
Calm down…
冷靜下來
Some transparent fungi grew on Haruka's face
姊姊的臉上長出了透明像菇類的東西
and her breathing got shallow.
據說呼吸越來越微弱了
What should I do? If Haruka just dies like this…
怎麼辦？要是姊姊就這樣死了…
That won't happen. I won't let it happen.
沒這回事…
Tsugumi! Take your medicine, okay?
繼實，吃藥吧
It's okay. Just take your medicine.
沒問題，先吃藥吧
Is this the shimeji mushroom-like thing that grew in his bedding?
那是長在棉被裡 像是鴻喜菇的東西嗎？
Yes, it is.
沒錯
Sorry for calling you out so early in the morning.
不好意思，這麼早請您過來
-What about him? -He has disappeared.
-他怎麼樣了？ -下落不明
If he is the reason that caused fungi to grow in the bedding,
若棉被裡長的菇類是源自於他
then is it possible that he caused the fungi
那津輕小姐的姊姊碰到的菌類
that's growing on Tsugaru's sister's face too?
或許也跟他有關吧？
Find him. I want to study more.
快把他找來，我想多做點調查
Dad.
爸爸…
You should just live here forever.
你只要一直生活在這裡就行了
You…
你…
You shouldn't approach humans.
不能靠近人類
You cannot survive in the human world.
你沒辦法在人類的世界裡生活
Am I…
我…
not human?
不是人類嗎？
Humans die.
人終有一死
You had died as a human.
身為人類的你已經死了
I…
我…
I am dead?
已經死了嗎？
And I brought you back to life.
是我讓你死而復生的
You're lying!
騙人…
I don't remember the time when I was alive
我沒有活著的記憶
and I don't remember that I died!
也沒有死掉的記憶！
I can only remember her face.
我只記得她的臉…
Only her face…
我只認識…
is what I thought I knew.
那張臉
And her face…
而那張臉
looked like she knew me too.
似乎也認識我
I wanted to know who I am so much…
我…是想知道自己是誰
I went after her.
才會追著她
My grandmother told me
據我奶奶所說
that this happened to her younger sister too.
奶奶的妹妹也是這樣
Her face was covered with the fungi-like thing too.
全身長滿了像這樣的菇類…
What happened to her?
她後來怎麼樣了？
In the end…
結果…
She didn't regain consciousness,
她沒能恢復意識
then she just…
就這樣…
So, my grandmother didn't know what happened to her as well.
所以…大家也不知道 她到底發生了什麼事
I don't want that.
我不要這樣…
I'm supposed to die before her.
要死也應該是我先死啊
Tsugumi.
繼實…
After all, I am…
我果然…
really not a human.
不是人類
I am not a human.
我不是人類
But…
但是…
you have only one relative.
你還有唯一一個家人
It is me.
就是我
I am the only one
我是唯一一個
who is by your side.
在你身邊的人
From now on.
今後…
For forever.
直到永遠
Look around you when you're sad.
要是感覺寂寞，就看看周圍吧
Look at the forest.
看看這片森林
You can survive here.
你可以在這裡活下去的
You can survive even though you're not human.
就算不是人類，也能活下去的
The trees in this deep forest
在這片森林深處的樹木
have been here for much longer than you
比你出現之前更久
and they're living here.
就一直活在這裡了
They haven't got a name,
就算沒有名字
they don't interact with humans,
就算沒跟人接觸
but they live here happily.
還是幸福地在這裡過活
I'm sure that they'll accept you too.
它肯定也會接受你的
Listen.
聽好了
If you think the only way to live is as a human, you couldn't be more wrong!
若認為生命只有人類這種形式 就大錯特錯了
You are not a dead person.
你在這裡不是死者
I gave you a new life.
是我…給予了你新的生命
Yes.
沒錯
You are a plant.
你…是植物
A plant.
植…物？
Yes.
沒錯
You're a plant that can think.
你是會思考的植物
I apologize…
留給你…
for letting such a painful function remain in you.
思考這種痛苦的機能
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
很抱歉…
But you are alive.
但是你活著
You are alive as you are now.
現在就像這樣活著
You're alive.
你還活著…
I am alive.
活著？
At the moment, it only depends on how much your sister wants to survive.
接著只能賭賭看令姊的生命力了
Tsugumi!
繼實！
-If you touch her recklessly-- -It's fine!
-別隨便碰她啊 -沒關係的
Haruka has been protecting me.
姊姊一直守護著我
She can't die before me.
居然會比我先死…
It's impossible. I won't let her.
不可能，我不會讓事情變這樣的
Good evening.
晚安
Oh… Who are you?
請問您是哪位？
-Sorry, I'm late. -Mr. Inaniwa.
-抱歉我來晚了 -學長
I'm Inaniwa, a post-grad student.
我是研究生稻庭
Excuse me…
您好
I told Professor Tsurumaru about this.
我跟鶴丸教授說了這件事
He told me to bring you this.
他叫我拿這個來
What is this?
這是什麼？
The essence extracted from a kind of fungi.
是某種菇類的抽取物
-Dr. Tsurumaru made it? -Yeah, I made it with him.
-教授他… -我跟教授一起做的
We hope it will be the wonder drug.
希望會是特效藥
You mean Dr. Tsurumaru knows the reason?
所以教授知道原因嗎？
Yeah. If it is true…
對，若這是真的…
this might cure her.
可能就能救你姊姊
What will you do?
怎麼樣？
I'll try it.
我要試試看
It's good.
可以了
Thank you.
謝謝
-Oh, right. -Over here?
-對 -在這裡嗎？
How is she?
怎麼樣了？
My sister is recovering, thanks to you.
託您的福，姊姊慢慢恢復了
She hasn't regained consciousness, but her vitals are stable.
雖然意識還沒恢復 但脈搏已經穩定下來
The doctor said her health should be okay now.
身體應該已經沒大礙了
This is the fungi we removed.
這是取出的菌類
How did you know, Professor?
教授怎麼會知道？
Why do you think that he was the reason?
您怎麼知道原因
I mean Ken Fukashi.
在深志研先生身上？
Considering the circumstances, I thought it was probable.
從情況看來，這可能性很高
This is what grew in the bedding that he slept in.
這是從他睡過的棉被長出來的
He had shimeji mushrooms,
可能是因為他吃了鴻喜菇
so it's possible that fungi like these had grown.
所以才長出了這種菌類
Fungi that looked like Red Thunder had grown here before too.
以前這裡也長出了 像是赤成君菇的菇類
We believe…
這個…
that he was the reason too.
應該也是源自於他
He keeps numerous fungi species in his body.
他的身上存在著無數的菌類
Your sister was infected with one of them. In that case…
你姊姊可能是感染到其中一種 若是這樣的話
I thought, another fungi species in his body
他體內的另一種菌
should work as a neutralizer.
或許會有中和劑的效用
You mean he is the host of such fungi?
您是說他是這種菌的宿主嗎？
You don't have to be so surprised.
這沒什麼好大驚小怪的
Humans are hosts to numerous kinds of fungi.
人類都是無數菌類的宿主
Yes, but…
話是這麼說沒錯…
But the resident microbiota that supports his body
只是支撐著他身體的常在菌
might not be something that we know of.
或許是我們還無法掌握的菌種
-They are unknown? -Yes.
-也就是未知的菌類嗎？ -沒錯
How the unknown fungi are born
但還不知道這些菌類是怎麼長出來
and how they are released aren't something I know.
又是怎麼被放出來的
If he has been releasing the spores of the fungi…
若擴散這種菌類孢子的就是他的話
Releasing spores?
孢子…
…I can say that…
他的存在
his very existence is a new fungi species itself.
可能就是新品種的菇類也說不定
He hasn't come back since that evening.
他從那天傍晚就沒回來了
He must have done something,
他果然是做了什麼
so he can't stay here anymore.
才會沒辦法繼續待在這裡
TSUGUMI TSUGARU
（津輕繼實）
What is that?
那是？
Here you are!
原來你在這裡啊？
My sister's life is saved.
我姊姊得救了
My sister won't die.
姊姊她…不會死的
Her disease will be cured.
病能治好的
Cured?
能治好？
Will you tell me what happened?
能請你告訴我發生了什麼事嗎？
I am studying fungi at university.
我在大學研究菇類
Perhaps…
或許你…
I can learn something from the problem you carry.
擁有的事物能讓我學習研究
-I want to know more-- -Miss Tsugaru.
-我想更加了解… -我無法繼續…
I can't stay with you.
待在津輕小姐你身邊了
I cannot stay with you.
我不能待在津輕小姐身邊
Please…
請你…
forgive me.
原諒我吧
don't find me again.
再來找我了
Sorry, he will not come back.
不好意思，他不會再回來了
You met him, didn't you?
你見到他了啊？
He said he wouldn't see you again, miss?
他跟這位美眉也說不再見面了啊？
Don't call her that. It's Miss Tsugaru.
別叫什麼美眉，是津輕小姐
Hey, just have dinner now. And do not make shimeji mushrooms.
好了，快點吃早餐 不准給我拿鴻喜菇出來
Okay, let's have dinner.
好，來吃飯吧
But it's a wonder.
但還真是不可思議
Why is Mr. Ken Fukashi's body still alive?
深志研先生的身體 到底是怎麼存活的呢？
Has he really been alive for over a hundred years?
該不會真的活了百年以上吧？
I guess he is happier to live in the forest.
或許在森林裡過活還比較幸福吧
Yeah, perhaps.
或許是吧
He must be afraid of being seen as a monster.
他肯定很害怕被當成怪物
Are you not afraid of him?
津輕小姐你不怕嗎？
Don't go see him alone again.
別再單獨去見他了
Mr. Inaniwa.
學長…
Yes?
什麼？
I cannot have a romantic relationship.
我沒辦法談戀愛
It's impossible for me to create a future with someone.
我沒辦法…跟誰一起創造未來
My future cannot be changed.
我的未來無法改變
From now on, can I…
我今後能在這裡
find out something else about myself besides my name here?
了解這名字以外的自己嗎？
-Yes? -Can I…
-什麼？ -我能夠…
find myself interesting?
讓自己變得有趣嗎？
Can I change myself?
我有辦法改變自己嗎？
You can.
可以的
I know you can change.
你一定會改變的
Let's change you!
讓我們一起改變吧
If you don't care what people think about you,
若是不畏懼他人的目光
you'll only either be a criminal or a real artist.
我想應該只能成為罪犯 或真正的藝術家了
Which one are you, Mr. Tokachi? An artist or a criminal?
十勝先生您呢？是藝術家還是罪犯？
I am none of them!
我都不是啊
I always care about what others think about me.
我非常在意別人怎麼看我
What? I don't think so.
我可不這樣覺得啊
You always say what you want and I thought you were carefree.
你總是有話直說 有時讓人覺得有點自以為是呢
Don't say that I am carefree!
什麼自以為是？你說話怎麼這樣？
I said it wrong. I mean it must feel so good.
我說錯了，是自我感覺良好吧
It's the same…
根本一樣啊
How rude of you!
你這女人還真失禮
I'm saying I live in a way that won't make people think so.
所以說我總是很小心 不讓別人這樣覺得我
Really, I'm always timid.
我真的是活得戰戰兢兢的
Oh, let's drop the topic or I'll be less popular.
別再說了，人氣會下降的
You see? I do care.
看吧？我很在意別人的眼光
It will be 3 p.m. soon, so let's call SNACK MAN here.
馬上就要三點了，來呼叫點心男吧
Where is he today?
他今天在哪裡呢？
The time of you and me
你和我的時間
The theory of evolution of me and you
我和你的進化論
If you are worried, tell Amakusa
有煩惱就問天草
Seek Amakusa's advice
去問問天草吧
Hello. This is Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
We received this problem.
我收到了這樣的煩惱
Thug Burdock from Chiba Prefecture, 17 years old.
是來自千葉縣的 金平牛蒡小子，17歲
"I had a fight with my friend,
和朋友吵架時
then I tweeted something bad about him without thinking.
我忍不住在推特說了朋友的壞話
It seems to have hurt my friend more than I thought.
結果這位朋友 比我想像中地還要受傷
I kept apologizing, but he wouldn't forgive me."
無論我怎麼道歉，對方都不原諒我
"I know I was wrong,
雖然我知道是我不對
but I have no other way to apologize.
但再道歉也沒用
How can I get him to forgive me?"
我該怎麼做才能獲得對方原諒呢？
So, we have come to a certain place in Tokyo.
就是這樣，今天我們來到都內某處
This is the office of the so-called yakuza,
這裡也就是所謂的893
that is, a criminal gang.
也就是黑道事務所的門口
I am going to risk my life to see how far you have to go
對於自己傷害了的人 要如何道歉才能獲得原諒
to apologize to a friend you have hurt.
我想親身測試看看
Someone that looks like a member has just come out.
看來有人出來了
Excuse me. Please let me interview you.
不好意思，請讓我訪問一下
-Hey, don't film my face, jerk! -It's okay, it's radio.
-別擅自拍我啊 -沒問題的，這是廣播
We won't broadcast your face.
不會拍到臉
We won't say your name or your group's name too.
也不會說出個人名字或團體名
What is it?
怎樣？
The police's control is stricter nowadays and it must be tough,
現在警方取締越來越嚴格了 肯定很辛苦
so why did you become a gang member?
您為何會成為黑道呢？
You ask me why?
問我為什麼？
It's because it's where a man belongs.
因為這才是男人的歸屬
You think you can't be better than others if you lead a normal life?
簡單地說，就是比不過普通人嗎？
What?
什麼？
You don't want to work or study,
因為不想工作，也不想讀書
so you think that you'll manage to survive in this world?
所以才想進入這世界 就會有辦法了嗎？
What are you talking about?
你在胡說什麼？
Does it feel good to use violence
就算被當成人渣
and make people surrender, even if others think that you're scum?
還是對於用暴力讓人屈服 而感到很爽嗎？
-Darn you! -I'm sorry…
-你這傢伙！ -很抱歉
You're looking down on me?
你瞧不起我嗎？
I apologize if I've hurt you.
要是你受傷了，我願意道歉
I'm sorry. Please forgive me!
很抱歉，請原諒我
Don't mess with me, you jerk!
少開玩笑了，這混蛋！
-Please stop it… -Sorry, it is a radio program.
-很抱歉，對不起… -我們只是在錄廣播…
Shut up, jerk!
混帳東西！
Looking at the result, no matter how much I apologized,
直接說結論，無論如何道歉
he didn't forgive me.
都不會被原諒的
But my opinion is…
但…但是，就我的想法來說
You don't apologize because you want the person's forgiveness,
道歉這件事本身 本來就不該以獲得原諒為前提
you should brace yourself for punishment when you do it!
而是要以受到懲罰為前提去做才對
Ouch…
好痛，痛…
If you don't prepare for the punishment when you apologize,
必須以受懲罰為前提才行
then you're just pretending to apologize
不然只是為了逃避自己的所作所為
to escape from what you did.
才裝做有心道歉的樣子而已
If you think that being hated by your friend is the punishment,
若是把被朋友討厭當成懲罰
accept it when you apologize!
就必須接受這一切再去道歉
Do not run away from what you did!
不能逃避自己的所作所為！
Please just don't damage the equipment.
抱歉，請放過我們的器材吧
-Take him inside. -Yes, Boss.
-帶他進去 -是
Stand up!
給我過來…
See you tomorrow.
明天再見
If you have worries in the afternoon…
點心時間…有煩惱…
Seek Amakusa's advice
去問問天草吧
You should've run away!
你應該要逃啊
You're not funny!
你還真無趣啊！
-Am I not? -You are not.
-是嗎？ -是啊
When people tell you their common worries,
或許你以為你在煩惱單元
you might want to give advice in a funny way,
回答得幽默又有趣
but you never really answer anything.
但你根本沒回答到問題
You are just making fun of other people's worries.
你只是在玩弄他人的煩惱而已
Are you aware of that?
你有自覺嗎？
No. I was trying to give advice in my own way.
不…我只是想照自己的方法 去回答而已
Yeah, Mr. Amakusa has tried his best.
是啊，天草先生很努力了
Mr. Tokachi, people who seek advice like it too.
十勝先生，聽眾的反應也不差啊
It's because they think that it's a story, right?
那是因為聽眾把這當成了梗
They give us a story, then it gets accepted,
自己提供的梗被採用了
so they are delighted!
是因為這樣才高興吧
You are not giving them advice about their worries!
但根本不是在幫人解決煩惱
People will grow tired of you soon enough,
你啊…這樣聽眾馬上會覺得膩
you'll be less and less funny, and it's over for you.
覺得你越來越不有趣 最後只能把節目收掉
What should I do then?
那…我該怎麼辦才好？
Exactly. What should he do?
就是說啊，該怎麼辦才好？
Give some proper advice.
好好回答就好了啊
Use your own words, in your own way.
用你自己的說法，像你的作風
I am learning very hard in my own way
我也很拼命地自己思考
to give people advice already.
作出回答的啊
Am I really not interesting?
我…果然不有趣嗎？
No, you aren't interesting.
是啊，你確實不有趣
Don't be defeated, Mr. Amakusa.
別被打敗了，天草先生
Your looks are deceptive.
你根本是虛有其表
-It's radio. His looks doesn't-- -You're annoying.
-廣播節目不看外在的啊… -煩死了
Don't say anything.
給我閉嘴
I thought you had a backbone and some spite!
我還以為你更有本事
I thought you wouldn't deceive people by playing cheap tricks.
沒想到你會是這種 靠小聰明蒙混過去的人
And what the heck is that song?
那首歌是怎樣？
It sounds like someone dull is going to come out now.
唱得一副以為自己 會引發風潮的樣子
-Who are you, Pikotaro? -Pikotaro is--
-以為自己是Piko太郎嗎？ -好像沒關連啊…
Don't say anything!
叫你閉嘴
You half-baked musicians
沒當成音樂人的傢伙
don't make an effort to pursue your dreams, that's why.
不上不下地追著夢就是這樣
No, that's not my intention.
我沒這種打算
I'm just trying to work hard at where I am now.
我只是想在這個歸屬好好努力而已
You don't belong anywhere!
你哪有什麼歸屬啊！
You're only part of my program!
你只是我節目的外景主持
Don't you dare play cheap tricks and try to draw attention!
區區一個外景主持 別給我動些小聰明想引人注目
If you want somewhere you belong to,
想要歸屬的話
fight fair and square with your words!
就好好地用話語去戰鬥！
Do it, Amakusa!
上吧，天草先生
Use your own words
用你自己的話語
to try and snatch it from me!
堂堂正正地掠奪我的地位啊！
How dare he say that.
還真好意思說呢
He never has his own words.
那傢伙根本從沒說過自己的話
He made the program's writers give me stories.
全部都讓廣播劇本家幫他想梗
If they aren't popular, he only thinks about how to fire them.
不好笑就只打算把人家開除
Well, that's not true
不，沒這回事
or he wouldn't be able to work for decades here.
光是這樣沒辦法做十幾年的
There you go.
久等囉
Yes, of course!
這還用說嗎？
I'm trying to comfort you,
我是打算安慰天草先生你
so at least go with it.
也給我捧場一下啊
Don't worry, Ushi. I don't feel down.
沒事的，阿牛，我沒因此沮喪
That's all right then.
那就好
But seriously, the part where you give people advice
但天草先生你的煩惱解答單元
is quite popular.
評價真的不差
For instance, my boss hasn't said anything about it.
上層也沒跟我說什麼
Ririe cheers for me too.
莉莉惠也一直在幫我加油呢
You'd better not trust her though.
最好別太相信她
Rumor has it that they're partners even in their private life.
據說那兩人私下也是伴侶
It looks like she is cheering for you
看起來像是裝作在幫天草先生你加油
to urge Mr. Tokachi to make greater efforts.
實際上是在激勵十勝先生
Wow, Ushi, you're so good at observing people.
阿牛，你還真會觀察人啊
I have to thank you for making me popular.
我能受到歡迎也是多虧有阿牛你
I'm so boring, but you make me interesting every time.
每次都讓無趣的我變得這麼有趣
I am really grateful to you.
我真的很感謝你
Will you think a bit more highly of yourself?
請你也自戀一點吧
I don't need your gratitude.
不用感謝我吧
Because I'm interesting too.
我也很有趣的
But people will grow tired of me soon if I'm only interesting.
但光只是有趣，馬上就會膩的
Does anyone ever listen to what I say?
我的話語難道 就真的無法觸動任何人心嗎？
You don't apologize because you want the person's forgiveness,
道歉這件事本身 本來就不該以獲得原諒為前提
you should brace yourself for punishment when you do it!
而是要以受到懲罰為前提去做才對
Don't run away from what you did!
不能逃避自己的所作所為！
Haruka.
姊姊…
Tsugumi?
繼實？
What a relief! I'll call the doctor here now.
太好了…我現在就去請醫生來
This is… the hospital?
這裡…是醫院嗎？
Yeah, the hospital you work at.
對，這裡是姊姊你工作的醫院
What happened to me?
我…發生什麼事了？
You don't remember anything?
你什麼都不記得了嗎？
Your head… Does your head hurt?
你的頭呢？不痛了嗎？
Tsugumi?
繼實？
Do you know where Miss Tsugumi Tsugaru is?
請問您知道津輕繼實小姐在哪裡嗎？
Who is Miss Tsugaru?
津輕小姐是誰啊？
Do you know Miss Tsugumi Tsugaru?
您認識津輕繼實小姐嗎？
No, I don't. Sorry.
不知道耶…很抱歉
Tsugaru?
津輕？
What is the first name?
津輕…什麼小姐？
It's Miss Tsugumi Tsugaru.
津輕繼實小姐
No, I don't.
不知道耶
I've never heard of her here.
沒在這附近聽過
-Look. -Oh, it's lovely.
-看 -真可愛呢
Do you know Miss Tsugaru?
您認識津輕繼實小姐嗎？
Tsugaru?
津輕小姐？
Her name is Tsugumi.
繼實小姐
The girl is Tsugumi though.
繼實就在這裡啊
What are you doing?
你要做什麼？
Miss Tsugaru is someone bigger.
津輕小姐比較大…
What?
什麼？
Do you know a big Tsugumi Tsugaru?
請問您認識大的津輕繼實小姐嗎？
A big one?
大的？
Not little Tsugumi.
不是小繼實
It's Miss Tsugumi Tsugaru.
是津輕繼實小姐
What does she do?
是做什麼的人？
Miss Tsugaru…
津輕小姐是…
She studies fungi.
研究菇類的人
Oh! So, she is a university student?
這…是大學生嗎？
Yes, she is.
對
In that case, why don't you ask the university?
那去大學問問看吧
Walk straight down this road.
從這裡直直走
There is only one university here,
這附近的大學只有這間
so it must be the one.
肯定在那裡吧
Hey!
等等
When you ask people something, you should at least say thank you.
跟人問事情，至少該說聲“謝謝”吧
Thank you, sir.
非常感謝您
SHIMEJI MUSHROOMS GREEN ASPARAGUS
（鴻喜菇 綠蘆筍）
You really like mushrooms.
你真的很喜歡菇類呢
Mommy!
媽媽…
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
-Is it enough for half a mat? -It's correct!
-這不夠半疊吧？ -明明就合啊
-Yeah, it's correct. -Yes, it is.
-真的有合呢 -明明就是合的
Oh? Ken!
研先生…
What are you doing?
你在做什麼啊？
I am looking for Miss Tsugaru.
我在找繼實小姐
Why are you here so shamelessly?
你怎麼好意思再跑來啊？
-I came to see Miss Tsugaru. -What?
我是來見津輕繼實小姐的
Where is Miss Tsugaru?
津輕繼實小姐在哪裡？
-Where can I see her? -Hey! Calm down.
-去哪裡才能見到她？ -冷靜下來
What an idiot.
真是個無聊的傢伙
-You are too naive. -Hey!
-簡直就太天真了 -喂
-Ken lost his memory. -Yeah.
-研先生可是失憶的人耶 -是啊
He just desperately wants someone's company.
無論如何就是想見到某人 這也是沒辦法的
But Ken, why do you want to see her?
但是，研先生 見到她後，你想怎麼做？
I want to apologize.
我會跟她道歉
You want her forgiveness?
你希望她原諒你嗎？
I am not apologizing because I want forgiveness.
我不是為了被原諒而道歉的
I'll apologize and prepare for the punishment I'll receive.
我會以受到懲罰為前提向她道歉
Punishment, huh? It's a good attitude.
懲罰啊…你很有決心
But you have to show her.
但是啊，這必須用態度來表示才行
Show her?
態度？
You have to show her that you are a decent person now.
要讓她看看你振作的一面啊
-I don't get what you mean. -Go to work, idiot!
-我不懂… -笨蛋，就是工作
Keep working and working and working.
工作…拼命工作
If you think even once that you want to play or take a rest…
要是給我再說什麼 “想玩”、“想休息”
then… die!
就給我…去死
"The Ballade for My Mother"!
《獻給母親的情歌》
Mr. Inaniwa made us hear it many times in the karaoke.
社長每次去卡拉OK都會唱
Ken Fukashi,
深志研先生
stop complaining and get to work, okay?
別再囉嗦了，快點來工作吧
The kanji of "work"…
所謂的工作
is composed of "people" and "move".
就是人…動起來的意思
Wait. Why did you all became Tetsuya Takeda?
為何大家都變金八老師了啊？
Okay, guys! Let's get to work!
好，大家來幹活吧
-Okay… -Thank you, Ken.
-是 -研先生，拜託囉
TSUGUMI TSUGARU
（津輕繼實）
-So, he is there? -Yeah.
-所以在你那邊啊？ -是
He is now working enthusiastically.
他現在很努力在工作呢
He came here to see Miss Tsugaru.
請那位美眉來看一下吧
Yeah.
好嗎？
Thank you.
拜託囉
He is here.
似乎回來了
Ken Fukashi has returned.
深志研回來了
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Why did you come back?
你為何回來了呢？
I am sorry.
對不起
Why do you apologize?
為什麼要道歉？
What happened here?
當時這裡到底發生了什麼事？
Do you apologize because you did something to my sister?
你會道歉…是因為 你對我姊姊做了些什麼嗎？
I am sorry.
對不起
You said you couldn't stay with me.
你說不能跟我待在一起
Then why did you come back?
那又為何回來了呢？
I came to apologize.
我是來道歉的
To ask for my forgiveness?
為了獲得原諒？
I am not apologizing because I want forgiveness.
我不是為了獲得原諒而道歉
For what, then?
那是為什麼？
My punishment.
請你…懲罰…
-Please give me my punishment. -Punishment?
-請你懲罰我 -懲罰？
I came to apologize and I've braced myself for the punishment.
我是以受到懲罰為前提向你道歉的
-I don't get what you're saying. -I am sorry.
-我不懂你在說什麼 -很抱歉
I am sorry!
對不起
I am sorry.
對不起…
What should I do?
我該怎麼做？
How do I give you a punishment? Please tell me.
我該怎麼做…才能懲罰你？請告訴我
I…
這…
I don't know how.
我也不知道
I don't know, so please tell me.
我不知道，所以請你告訴我
What is a punishment?
懲罰是什麼？
I should be the one to apologize.
我才要道歉
Why do you apologize?
為何津輕小姐你要道歉？
It was my fault.
是我的錯
Because I…
都是我…
I brought you here from the forest.
強硬地把你拉到這裡
No, it isn't your fault.
不是這樣的
I am sorry.
對不起
You don't have to apologize for it.
你不需要為此道歉
I don't want you to apologize to me.
我不希望津輕小姐向我道歉
I apologize. I'm so sorry.
我要道歉，對不起
Please give me my punishment.
請懲罰我
Please…
請對我…
do what you did to my sister.
做做看你對姊姊做的事
You touched her?
你碰到她了嗎？
Does that happen if you touch me?
碰到就會變成那樣嗎？
In that case, please touch me.
那就請你碰我吧
It's okay for me.
我沒問題的
Because…
我…
I'm not afraid of dying.
不害怕死亡
The blood streams in my head might be blocked or break anytime.
就算腦血管突然破裂或阻塞都不意外
My mother too had the disease at 30 years old and died at 34.
我母親也是30歲發病 34歲就死了
I have had it since I was little and I might die anytime.
我則是從小就發病了 無論何時死掉都不意外
So, please touch me.
所以…請你碰我吧
-No! -Don't do this!
不行的，別這樣
Mr. Ken Fukashi!
深志研先生
Please…
我…
show me what you really are.
請讓我看看你真正的樣子
Please don't come here!
請不要過來！
Please…
不要…
don't come here.
過來這裡
Please.
求求你…
We won't.
我們不會過去的
I'll take care of the rest.
接下來就交給我吧
I'll keep a close eye on him.
我會好好看著他的
Keep an eye on him?
看著他？
There are ways to investigate without using force.
不用強硬的手段還是能調查
Anyway, just go home. I'll take care of the rest.
總之你今天先回去吧，剩下的交給我
Take care.
路上小心
Hey!
嘿
Can I go there?
我可以過去你那邊嗎？
Where is Miss Tsugaru?
津輕小姐呢？
She's gone.
回去了
Can I go there?
你還好吧？
You can.
我沒事
Come on.
好了
Let's return to the house.
回家吧
House?
家？
Our house.
我們的家
Miss Tsugaru understands too.
津輕小姐也同意了
Can I…
我…
Can I continue to stay here?
還可以繼續待在這裡嗎？
Of course.
當然
So, you don't have to apologize.
所以你不用再道歉了
In your life, if you're with someone,
只要一起活下去
things like that happen.
總是會遇到這種事
What do you mean?
什麼事？
Being with someone else…
和某人一起活下去
to humans,
對人類來說…
it's already something like a punishment.
已經是一種懲罰了
Come on.
來
Let's go.
我們走吧
Is he a monster?
他果然是怪物嗎？
I might kill another person.
我…或許又要殺人了
Ken, run!
快逃啊！
Come and live in the human world with me.
和我一起在人類世界活下去吧